<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-02-03T11:56:34-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">forgash_</title><subtitle>data analytics powered by flipside crypto, sql, dbt and coffee. A full list of submitted bounties can be found in the menu ↗️, full posts (new) are extrapolations of bounty prompts ... ⛓📊</subtitle><author><name>Jack Forgash</name></author><entry><title type="html">Anchor - Growing Pains</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/02/03/anchor.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Anchor - Growing Pains" /><published>2022-02-03T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2022-02-03T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/02/03/anchor</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/02/03/anchor.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Unpacking the road to 6bn in deposits, 10bn in TVL, and the aftermath of the degenbox fiasco.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;disclaimer&quot;&gt;Disclaimer&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I have a vested stake in the terra ecosystem and own assets described in this write-up. All data is sourced from Flipside Crypto’s database index of the Terra blockchain. In no way in this financial advice and I am neither seeking to boost nor harm Anchor Protocol. Data is data.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;📊 All charts replicated here are &lt;a href=&quot;https://forgash.retool.com/embedded/public/a8941498-3423-446f-a60d-32763d875a83&quot;&gt;interactive on Retool&lt;/a&gt;, where they will continuously update.&lt;br /&gt;
My data models behind these charts are open source and available on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/forgxyz/flipside&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;1/ December was Anchor’s best month yet with over $2.6B new &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/search?q=%24UST&amp;amp;src=ctag&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;$UST&lt;/a&gt; deposits. 🚀 The surge in deposits helped propel Anchor’s TVL over $10B just 9 months after launch. But that’s not the only thing that happened in December… 🧵&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Anchor Protocol (@anchor_protocol) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/anchor_protocol/status/1480732475223461888?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;January 11, 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I initially set out to provide some simple context to this major headline and had planned to write about how Anchor protocol was sitting on 6bn in deposits and 10bn in TVL, fueled by users and protocols alike flocking to 20% in low-risk yield. These are both numbers to be celebrated, but it would be wrong to not dive in and provide deeper context around what’s happened within Anchor over the past two months. So, this is coming a bit later due to some obvious factors: The Wonderland drama unfolding over the final weeks of January. Do Kwon’s tweet offering to recapitalize the reserve with upwards of $300mm. The Anchor v2 announcement and roadmap for greater revenue generation to sustain a higher reserve. Anchor has been the center of attention recently, for better or for worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;growth&quot;&gt;Growth&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On November 24th, 2021 the gross balance of Anchor Earn was 2.13bn in user deposits. By year end, that number crossed $5,000,000,000. Yes I am writing out all the zeros to show just how big that number is. But, 5bn alone is not a crazy TVL, it’s the $3bn in depositor growth over 37 days that is eye catching. Now, we all know about the Wonderland fiasco, so I’ll stick to the numbers here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;November 24th is not an arbitrary date. I’ve identified this as an inflection point in Anchor as it is the first day we see an individual deposit greater than 100mm UST. Over the remainder of the year, there were 6 additional &amp;gt;100mm deposits into Anchor Earn, totaling &lt;strong&gt;1.25bn&lt;/strong&gt; UST in deposits over &lt;a href=&quot;https://app.flipsidecrypto.com/dashboard/anchor-protocol-yEpGtX&quot;&gt;just 7 transactions in 2021&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: One of these deposits (100mm) is actually not the degenbox but an individual. Further, one can investigate these addresses and find a significant number of deposits &amp;lt;100mm. Community members, like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kobiOyU092M&amp;amp;t=425s&quot;&gt;danku_r&lt;/a&gt;, have identified a figure closer to 1.6bn as the deposit impact. Finally, we are clearly not done yet as there was just a 131mm deposit on February 1st.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;8u 12u$(medium)&quot;&gt;
		&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/2022/2/anchor/1.png&quot; class=&quot;image fit&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, it would be wrong to jump to the conclusion that the degenbox alone put the pressure on Anchor. We can clearly see that the gross volume passing through Anchor had been steadily increasing by looking at the max daily transaction size. Well before the whale dumps, users were regularly comfortable dropping tens of millions in and out of Anchor on a daily basis. The young stable coin, UST, had and has been tested through several market dumps and 20% is an astounding rate for cash. Plus, Terra is fast, low-fee and has plenty of bridges so why not park idle funds in Anchor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;6u 12u$(small)&quot;&gt;
		&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/2022/2/anchor/2.png&quot; class=&quot;image fit&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;6u 12u$(small)&quot;&gt;
		&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/2022/2/anchor/3.png&quot; class=&quot;image fit&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;total-net-transaction-flow&quot;&gt;Total Net Transaction Flow&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another view that we’ll jump into quickly is net transaction flows through anchor. That is, the absolute sum of deposits, redemptions and liquidations happening on Anchor Earn. Why? This gives us another picture of what is happening on the protocol, from a very high level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;8u 12u$(medium)&quot;&gt;
		&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/2022/2/anchor/4.png&quot; class=&quot;image fit&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple highlights here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The 11/24 net flows were at or around 25bn&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;On 12/31, the net flows total 38bn&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compare this to the net 3bn increase in Earn deposits and this is where the theme of the story gets a bit more clear. Of the 13bn in transaction flow from 11/24-12/31, 23% remained in Anchor as a deposit whereas it took 25bn in gross transaction volume for the first 2bn in Earn deposits - a capture rate of just 8%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a story of balance, Anchor Protocol needs to balance revenue from the borrow side with the costs of paying depositors. The Yield Reserve is, in effect, a measure of that balance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the late summer and into the fall, as Anchor passed 1bn then 2bn in deposits, the protocol had little issue supporting this growth. Total Collateral Value increased in (mostly) lock-step and the yield reserve gently ticked up. 20% was, for a time, sustainable, because the value of collateral exceeded the amount of deposits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;8u 12u$(medium)&quot;&gt;
		&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/2022/2/anchor/4b.png&quot; class=&quot;image fit&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What you’re seeing here is the growth of deposits and collateral value, from 3/17 to 9/1, on a relative scale. So, the 3/17/2021 value for each is set to 100. Total Collateral Value and Earn Depositor Balance move in tandem. That’s good - it’s what Anchor needs to support the high yield figure of 20%&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;20% is a big number, and there’s been a lot of discussion recently on sustainability of Anchor Protocol to continue offering this fantastic rate. I’ll point out, as I often do when talking about this, that the 20% was expected to be unsustainable over the long run. &lt;em&gt;The yield will not be 20% forever, and that is by design. Market forces will determine the yield in a mature protocol.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are mechanics in place to hold the yield at 20% while the protocol scales and the plan is to release the peg to market forces when Anchor is fully capable. It is still in v1, only on the mother chain, and supports just two forms of bonded collateral. Plans for v2 have recently been announced, go read about that here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;1/ Let’s talk about Anchor’s V2 Borrow Model which will enable Anchor to rapidly onboard compound liquid staking derivatives like &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/search?q=%24LUNAx&amp;amp;src=ctag&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;$LUNAx&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/search?q=%24sAVAX&amp;amp;src=ctag&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;$sAVAX&lt;/a&gt; as new collateral types.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;What does the borrowing process look like in V2 &amp;amp; how does interest for borrower’s work? 🧵👇&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Anchor Protocol (@anchor_protocol) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/anchor_protocol/status/1488208834795610118?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;January 31, 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;balance&quot;&gt;Balance&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Anchor team made a point on the recent &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/flipsidecrypto/status/1486867269871362054?s=20&amp;amp;t=Go-gxEdSvBZATvTm5hOA7w&quot;&gt;community call with Flipside Crypto&lt;/a&gt; that stuck with me. The Yield Reserve is &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; measure but not &lt;strong&gt;the&lt;/strong&gt; measure. Collateral and borrowing generate real income for Anchor and this is what sustains the rate. The Yield Reserve is a measure of that profit balance - and it is an important one - but this comment inspired me to put forth these additional protocol metrics. The conversation has to grow if Anchor is to…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I said the core of this write-up, and the core of Anchor in particular, is balance. Total Collateral Value needs to be a factor greater than Earn deposits in order to meet the 20% APY target. This is because bLUNA yields about 10%, bETH around 5% (per LIDO) and borrowing costs 11.4% presently. None of these individual components are enough to generate sufficient revenue to pay 20% to depositors. So, scaling is a careful balance between the two competing sides of Anchor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anchor Earn is both incredibly attractive and the devs have made it a priority that embedding access to Anchor’s 20% savings rate is just a few lines of code. Scaling the Earn side is easy business and with that “Stripe for Savings” mantra, we would expect the proliferation of Anchor Earn to outpace the Borrow side. This is naturally a problem, because that’s the side that pays the bills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s where we get to the second risk factor, which I would argue is a far bigger problem than the degenbox, because it is absolutely central to the protocol. Collateral has not grown, at least not naturally. In an “up only” market like we just had in Q4, a lot of problems can be masked with macro figures like $10bn TVL and looking at Total Collateral Value but not actual collateral amounts. Using the above chart, I showed how collateral value was growing alongside deposits over the first six months of Anchor. That’s true, from a high level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, here’s what has really been going on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;8u 12u$(medium)&quot;&gt;
		&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/2022/2/anchor/5.png&quot; class=&quot;image fit&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This chart is similarly setting the starting date, in this case September 1st, to 100 so we can compare relative growth. However, instead of bLUNA &lt;em&gt;value&lt;/em&gt;, we’re looking at the count of bLUNA captured by Anchor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In mid-August, &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/posts/2022/2/anchor/netAPR.png&quot;&gt;ANC incentives to borrowers&lt;/a&gt; fell to a natural rate of around net 0% (thanks &lt;a href=&quot;https://app.alphadefi.fund/anchor&quot;&gt;Alpha DeFi&lt;/a&gt; for this chart) and bLUNA bonded to Anchor plummeted from 80mm to 60mm. It’s stayed there ever since. Sure, bETH has been onboarded and that helps… a bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, I’ll drop a positive note here. On the recent &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/flipsidecrypto/status/1486867269871362054?s=20&amp;amp;t=Go-gxEdSvBZATvTm5hOA7w&quot;&gt;Anchor x Flipside community call&lt;/a&gt;, the Anchor team mentioned that, during this dip, the value of bETH had remained flat. In other words, as ETH fell from $4k to $2500, users increased bonding and base bETH increased. This is true, and bETH has had some tremendous growth in 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;8u 12u$(medium)&quot;&gt;
		&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/2022/2/anchor/6.png&quot; class=&quot;image fit&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I put together &lt;a href=&quot;https://forgash.retool.com/embedded/public/ccb5c638-73de-4f99-9669-65b8919762f5&quot;&gt;a dashboard&lt;/a&gt; tracking exactly this collateral growth for a Flipside bounty. Feel free to take a quick look.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-balance-upset&quot;&gt;The Balance Upset&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two tremors are not enough to rock a foundation, but they set the stage for drama. Anchor continued to generate higher levels of income because the yield generated by bLUNA was continuously worth more as the price rocketed to ATHs all Fall into December. But, because the protocol was unable to garner new interest in the Borrow side in the form of fresh bLUNA, the ability to generate revenue began to lose ground to the explosive growth in Anchor Earn deposits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, how exactly did this open Anchor to excess risk?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;8u 12u$(medium)&quot;&gt;
		&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/2022/2/anchor/7.png&quot; class=&quot;image fit&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;At its peak, on 12/9, the reserve was 78.9mm&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Over just the 7 largest Q4 transactions, Earn grew by 1.25bn. At 20% yield, this costs the protocol 20.83mm in yield per month&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;On 1/28, the yield reserve sat at 38.7mm, down 40mm in under 2 months
We know that the excess deposits cannibalized the yield reserve, but the macro conditions added further pressure, driving the value of Anchor’s collateral down and thus the revenue generated plummeted and the reserve continued to take a beating.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I know others have identified a number closer to 1.6bn as the degenbox Earn deposit due leveraging up … I am choosing to isolate these mega transactions. Thus, the cost is likely higher.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had the market stayed hot, or at least not hit a dip, the reserve would still be leaking away. It’s possible to calculate what the reserve might currently be had LUNA stayed in the $80 range, but that is not what happened and I find that to be an unnecessary exercise at the moment. One of Flipside’s bounty prompts this week tasked analysts with estimating the natural yield, so keep an eye out from them for some work on that front. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/danku_r/status/1488281287760752642?s=20&amp;amp;t=Go-gxEdSvBZATvTm5hOA7w&quot;&gt;danku_r&lt;/a&gt; has also worked through this estimate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;where-do-we-go-from-here&quot;&gt;Where do we go from here?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, and foremost, it is massively important to remember that the yield reserve is but one metric measuring the success of Anchor Protocol. Some could call it the measure of profitability, but I prefer to look at it through the lens of balance. Anchor launched in March 17th, 2021. It’s not a year old yet and has, so far, weathered some rocky markets and a yield locust swarm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One final explanation of the yield reserve and how Anchor works. Deposits are captured in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://finder.extraterrestrial.money/mainnet/address/terra1sepfj7s0aeg5967uxnfk4thzlerrsktkpelm5s&quot;&gt;Anchor Market Contract&lt;/a&gt; and aUST is minted and transferred to the user. aUST accrues value at the Earn APY and can be redeemed at any time from Anchor Protocol. The initial deposit is paid from the Market Reserve and accrued interest that cannot be covered by collateral revenue is siphoned from the yield reserve. As of this writing, the Market contract holds 3.9bn in UST on 5.2bn in deposits. That is a &lt;strong&gt;75%&lt;/strong&gt; reserve ratio. (The rest is currently borrowed by users out via collateralized lending at a maximum LTV of 60%). Consider the fact that the Fed &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.federalreserve.gov/monetarypolicy/reservereq.htm&quot;&gt;dropped the reserve requirement to 0% in March of 2020&lt;/a&gt; and have left it there and let me know if you think 75% is conservative enough to mitigate a bank run on Anchor… (&lt;a href=&quot;https://fred.stlouisfed.org/series/TOTRESNS&quot;&gt;Just because banks do not have to hold a reserve, at the moment, does not mean they are doing so. Reserves are actually at an ATH&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My takeaway from this tumultuous month is the massive need to address Anchor’s revenue generation. The link between incentivized borrowing and bLUNA growth is clear. bETH has been a successful test of alternative collateral options for users, but it hasn’t been enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent days, the Anchor team released the roadmap to v2 and, for me, this provides a lot of context to &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/stablekwon/status/1485874118029635589?s=20&amp;amp;t=eqHHtH17mv_uQQ3l_UiOGQ&quot;&gt;Do Kwon’s tweet&lt;/a&gt; regarding recapitalizing the yield reserve. I’ll add a bit of opinion here - I do not think only refilling the coffers with hundreds of millions is the move, even if it is just to buy time until v2 can be implemented. I understand the move, but I believe there are additional moves that could accompany a recapitalization. These interests seem aligned, as I share in the goal to reduce Anchor’s dependency on bLUNA:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;12/ Goal is to drop luna dominance in anchor collateral under 40% by growing adoption of other assets - should grow utilization rate.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Do Kwon 🌕 (@stablekwon) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/stablekwon/status/1486878333946118145?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;January 28, 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not over yet. Anchor has proven to be a highly desirable destination of capital and the promise of real yield for consumers is a formidable goal. v1 has forged admirable milestones in its first year of operation and I am optimistic and excited to see what is in store for v2. As I have made clear, it is my opinion that attracting collateral and capturing yield is absolutely essential and, thus far, the roadmap is leading us in the right direction. Time will tell if Anchor is able to execute.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jack Forgash</name></author><category term="terra" /><category term="anchor" /><category term="collateral" /><summary type="html">Unpacking the road to 6bn in deposits, 10bn in TVL, and the aftermath of the degenbox fiasco.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/posts/2022/2/anchor/link_photo.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/posts/2022/2/anchor/link_photo.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Through the Wormhole</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/12/04/wormhole.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Through the Wormhole" /><published>2021-12-04T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-12-04T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/12/04/wormhole</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/12/04/wormhole.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-theme=&quot;dark&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;1/ The &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/wormholecrypto?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@wormholecrypto&lt;/a&gt; support for Terra in the V2 UI is live! &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Transfers of &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/search?q=%24UST&amp;amp;src=ctag&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;$UST&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/search?q=%24LUNA&amp;amp;src=ctag&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;$LUNA&lt;/a&gt; between Terra, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ethereum?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@ethereum&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/solana?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@solana&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/BinanceChain?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@BinanceChain&lt;/a&gt; via Wormhole’s cross-chain bridge are now available :) &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/2gWsIq2KxW&quot;&gt;https://t.co/2gWsIq2KxW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Terra (UST) 🌍 Powered by LUNA 🌕 (@terra_money) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/terra_money/status/1450538513141690371?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;October 19, 2021&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a lot out there already written about what Wormhole is and how to use it. This isn’t going to be one of those articles. Two recent Flipside bounties asked the community analysts to investigate user behavior in the weeks since Wormhole was enabled for Terra. I really enjoyed those so I created a whole website just to write more about my work on those (and future) bounties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;terra-bounties-101--103&quot;&gt;Terra Bounties 101 &amp;amp; 103&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As many of them often are, two recent Terra analytics bounties were closely inter-related. The primary question for 101 was a call to analyze initial user behavior with Wormhole v2, focusing on what they’re sending and to where. 103 honed in on UST, aka the Terra dollar. I’ve loved analyzing UST - where it is, where it’s going, and how it’s being used (I’ll definitely be revisiting a lot of my work on Anchor Protocol for some more comprehensive write-ups) so of course I jumped into these two prompts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basis of this is my work on these bounties:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://app.flipsidecrypto.com/dashboard/into-the-wormhole-Sqv35x&quot;&gt;My submission (101)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://app.flipsidecrypto.com/dashboard/usd-terra-usd-v5wGyB&quot;&gt;My submission (103)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note - images are linked to an interactive version of the chart until embeds are fixed. From there, you can download via csv or see the SQL to reproduce and further explore the data. Most charts are from the above bounties, but I did create a few new ones for this post.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post, I am going to use t$. This is the denomination symbol I am giving to terra dollars and will be using this going forward rather than assuming equivalent value in USD. Basically, it’s count of UST (because 1=1) plus LUNA (or whatever other token) in UST value. When a chart is scaled to token count, instead, that will be made clear. Basically, t$ means UST.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Very briefly&lt;/strong&gt;, what is Wormhole?&lt;br /&gt;
It’s a decentralized, cross-chain, token bridge. Users will find it somewhat similar to the native Terra Bridge, but with support for more chains. That’s about all I am going to say about it here because Terraform Labs has already written an &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/terra-money/wormhole-v2-for-terra-the-ui-walkthrough-595ca6649ae8&quot;&gt;extensive blog post&lt;/a&gt; on Wormhole. One final note of import is that the eventual plan is for Wormhole to supplant the Bridge due to its decentralized nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;-into-the-wormhole-we-go&quot;&gt;👨‍🚀 Into the Wormhole We Go&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Access to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://wormholebridge.com/&quot;&gt;Wormhole Token Bridge&lt;/a&gt; kicked-off with that tweet on October 19th and immediately we see some large outflow of UST. Now, this was mainly one single transaction of 30mm, so in reality it took a couple days for user behavior to rev up.&lt;br /&gt;
The &lt;a href=&quot;https://finder.extraterrestrial.money/mainnet/address/terra1dtzfwgzt8xa70zkm8gqzwz0n4zrqtngdpqejx5&quot;&gt;same address&lt;/a&gt; sent the next 30mm on October 30th. I almost got pulled into a rabbit hole by trying to figure out who or what that address is, but we’re talking wormholes, here, not rabbit holes. Maybe later (probably later).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;8u 12u$(medium)&quot;&gt;
		&lt;a href=&quot;https://velocity-app.flipsidecrypto.com/velocity/visuals/ee9092ae-c16d-482a-861e-ec3cbf951681/7cb23054-67de-4de3-b966-da8cb5960c86&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/2021/12/wormhole/outbound_gross_volume.png&quot; class=&quot;image fit&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;4u 12u$(small)&quot;&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;
			&lt;div style=&quot;color:#58aabf&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;#9632; Solana&lt;/div&gt;
			&lt;div style=&quot;color:#CEB0FA&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;#9632; Ethereum&lt;/div&gt;
			&lt;div style=&quot;color:#f3ba2b&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;#9632; Binance Smart Chain&lt;/div&gt;
			&lt;div style=&quot;color:black&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;#9632; Polygon&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;Click chart for interactive version.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;a href=&quot;https://velocity-app.flipsidecrypto.com/velocity/visuals/f468585c-aa8a-4ad0-887a-42caf798c33c/b85415e4-3e70-4fe9-a7a8-86032dd5edfb&quot;&gt;Just UST&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
		&lt;a href=&quot;https://velocity-app.flipsidecrypto.com/velocity/visuals/28d49c65-f4a5-46a2-878f-5c91d5788791/dc2a21d3-0e22-4d0a-879c-d7f658de8b65&quot;&gt;Just LUNA&lt;/a&gt;


	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;️-bound-for-the-sun&quot;&gt;☀️ Bound for the Sun&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;10u 12u$(medium)&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;image right&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://velocity-app.flipsidecrypto.com/velocity/visuals/dcd50746-5230-4c87-b6bc-7304937cd7cd/7dc9927c-1d6d-427d-a6bd-116d3f069aff&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/2021/12/wormhole/destination_donut.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
		We set out to analyze the initial activity, right? &lt;br /&gt;
		Solana.  &lt;br /&gt;
		That&apos;s the initial activity. A lot of value was sent over to Solana in the first ~two months since Wormhole v2 support was added to the Terra network. This shouldn&apos;t come as a surprise, as the &lt;a href=&quot;https://bridge.terra.money/&quot;&gt;native Terra bridge&lt;/a&gt; already supports Ethereum, Binance Smart Chain and Harmony. Wormhole offers users another way to get to Ethereum and BSC but Solana is the new kid on the block, and Terra users nearly exclusively used Wormhole to get over to Solana. This donut is percent of total outbound value (t$), thru December 3rd. Over that time period, users have send $185.3mm in LUNA and UST, primarily to Solana and Ethereum.&lt;br /&gt;
		&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;2u 12u$(medium)&quot;&gt;
		&lt;div style=&quot;color:#2475b4&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;#9632; Solana&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;div style=&quot;color:#fd7d13&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;#9632; Ethereum&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;div style=&quot;color:#34a42d&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;#9632; BSC&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;div style=&quot;color:#d41429&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;#9632; Polygon&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://app.flipsidecrypto.com/velocity/visuals/60556a3f-15b0-46d6-8d6b-ba1cf613c922/5ece72b0-370c-4105-9221-2c8a2b655498&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/2021/12/wormhole/outbound_cumulative.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;image left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://velocity-app.flipsidecrypto.com/velocity/visuals/05aae2b1-04c0-4f16-864e-ede79214d59f/e7593818-5b25-4eb0-979a-22b5c9bc64aa&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/2021/12/wormhole/outbound_token_donut.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;div style=&quot;color:#ffffdd&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;#9632; UST&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;div style=&quot;color:#eff8b9&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;#9632; LUNA&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
A significant majority of this outflow has been the stablecoin, UST. This is not wholly surprising for a few reasons. LUNA is the native chain token. It secures the network, it can be bonded, it can be used as collateral ... ultimately, it&apos;s most useful on the mother chain (though Terra does need solid LUNA/UST pools across inter-chain networks 🌐). UST, on the other hand, is money, let it fly 💸.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, it seems users are pretty excited to have direct access to bridge their UST from Terra over to Solana. Context is always important, so let’s take a look at just how much UST has been sent to Solana, and how much already exists across the major chains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;8u 12u$(medium)&quot;&gt;

		&lt;a href=&quot;https://velocity-app.flipsidecrypto.com/velocity/visuals/2ce68b68-f43a-4e15-bcc2-7bb8cf64e8e0/b85415e4-3e70-4fe9-a7a8-86032dd5edfb&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/2021/12/wormhole/cumulative_ust.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;4u 12u$(medium)&quot;&gt;

		Per the respective block scanners, the supply of wrapped UST (as of this writing) is:  
		&lt;ul&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://etherscan.io/token/0xa47c8bf37f92abed4a126bda807a7b7498661acd&quot;&gt;800mm on Ethereum&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bscscan.com/token/0x23396cf899ca06c4472205fc903bdb4de249d6fc&quot;&gt;22mm on BSC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://polygonscan.com/token/0x692597b009d13c4049a947cab2239b7d6517875f&quot;&gt;7.4mm on Polygon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;

		... 125mm to Solana is a lot 💪  &lt;br /&gt;
		... in 6 weeks is fast ⚡️
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-the-catch&quot;&gt;What’s the catch?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;6u 12u$(small)&quot;&gt;
		Finally, I was interested in *who* is sending money through the wormhole. Is it whales, like those $30mm transfers? Or is it the everydayman, just looking for some low-fee yield? Turns out, it&apos;s a bit of both. We can look at the spread of transfer size to determine the type of user that&apos;s sending money through the wormhole. I did have to set an upper limit at $4mm as the chart scaling skews representation on the smaller end. &lt;a href=&quot;https://velocity-app.flipsidecrypto.com/velocity/visuals/0bf8920d-12d1-40b7-bf54-c2726c1523e4/c87a857d-4abd-4fc9-b16c-578e243d0809&quot;&gt;Here&apos;s an un-capped chart&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
		&lt;br /&gt;
		I was, frankly, surprised to see the extensive spread of transfers &amp;gt;t$100,000. I can throw some hypothese out there, but a look at LUNA&apos;s price action might be lending a helping hand to these large transactions. Today, LUNA recently overtook DOGE as the 10th largest cryptocurrency, by marketcap, and has made quite a lot of people quite a lot of money. However, that&apos;s not the point of this writeup, so we&apos;ll move on.&lt;br /&gt;
		&lt;br /&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;6u 12u$(medium)&quot;&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;image fit&quot;&gt;
			&lt;a href=&quot;https://velocity-app.flipsidecrypto.com/velocity/visuals/85e89ec9-714a-4120-b211-e6641830d719/f29cf5ec-f7dc-46d9-876b-1e10a3ba31cb&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/2021/12/wormhole/ust_transfer_spread.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Affluent wallets are readily sending their UST through the wormhole. The direct Terra-Solana connection is long awaited, and we can see the immediate impact of the past six weeks. At some point soon™️, Flipside will announce Solana tables and bounties and all that analytical goodness. Where this UST is going and what users are doing with it is something I’m incredibly interested in. For now, I expect users will continue to utilize this new chain connection and we’ll see a steady stream of UST exports off the Terra blockchain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;-who-is-using-what&quot;&gt;👥 Who is using what&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I looked at this 10 days ago, the story was looked quite different. When I wrote bounty 101, Bridge users (daily unique wallets) were down 25% since Wormhole launched and it looked like users were fleeing the old for the new. Running the query today, we see user activity has rebounded from it’s local minimum while Wormhole has continued to attract users. This is why updating analyses is important and no conclusion is really ever set in stone - this isn’t a predictive piece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned above, the plan is for Wormhole to become the primary bridge to and from Terra, so one day this point will be moot. Further, we know that Solana is the primary destination for users going through the Wormhole and when you send UST through, it does get wrapped. Users do have to send a transaction through on the other side to confirm and claim the whUST, so it would make sense that the native bridge remains option one for Ethereum, as there are fewer fee-incurring transactions with that bridge. If users have to unwrap UST when it hits Ethereum and the only bridge available is Wormhole, we may see some problems continuing to scale UST on Ethereum in the future due to fee friction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Take note that the bridge is fixed to the left axis and wormhole to the right. Flipside is working on fixing charts to show both scales when this is the case.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;image fit&quot;&gt;
	&lt;a href=&quot;https://app.flipsidecrypto.com/velocity/visuals/e2edefe4-eb2e-4966-9ecb-fc8fc9c3080b/0f267f10-5c50-4a69-8d9f-4762bb6ef612&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/2021/12/wormhole/users_comp.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;-whats-next&quot;&gt;🎬 What’s next?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This didn’t encompass everything I took a look at for the bounties. In &lt;a href=&quot;https://app.flipsidecrypto.com/dashboard/into-the-wormhole-Sqv35x&quot;&gt;my submission for 101&lt;/a&gt;, I took a look at alternate stablecoins coming through the Wormhole to Terra. Volume is still relatively low, so not worth expanding on at this point in time. However, it will remain interesting to see if users bring over USDC, Dai or Tether for some reason. Terra is an entire blockchain built to create and support the decentralized stablecoin UST, so I see no reason to have pools of alternate stables but others have different preferences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wormhole is also enabling wrapped tokens of all origins on Terra. In that same submission (101), I provide a table of known wrapped tokens that users have sent to Terra. Volume is few and far between, at this time, so I haven’t yet expanded that view. However, it is expected that more and more tokens will be made available to users of the Terra blockchain. &lt;a href=&quot;https://dex.loop.markets/&quot;&gt;LOOP&lt;/a&gt; has already enabled whWBTC and whWETH pools. Wormhole support is a huge step forward for Terra because of this. There are a lot of great native protocols on Terra, but it’s a young ecosystem. Having access to these (wrapped) tokens provides foundational support to the entire Terra ecosystem. We’ll see how it develops.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Jack Forgash</name></author><category term="terra" /><category term="wormhole" /><summary type="html">Introduction 1/ The @wormholecrypto support for Terra in the V2 UI is live! Transfers of $UST and $LUNA between Terra, @ethereum, @solana, and @BinanceChain via Wormhole’s cross-chain bridge are now available :) https://t.co/2gWsIq2KxW&amp;mdash; Terra (UST) 🌍 Powered by LUNA 🌕 (@terra_money) October 19, 2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/wormhole.gif" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/wormhole.gif" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>